In this video, I'm going to talk about convolusional neural networks for hundred
在本视频中 我们会介绍卷积神经网络
and digit recognition. This was one of the big success stories of
在手写数字识别中的应用 这是神经网络在1980s几个成功应用之一
neuron networks in the 1980s. The deep convolutional nets developed by
由 Yann LeCun 和他的合作者们开发的 深度卷积神经网络
Yann LaCun and his collaborators did a really good job of recognizing handwriting
在识别手写数字方面表现出色
and were actually used in practice. They're one of the few examples from that
并投入到实际应用当中 这是为数不多的
period of deep neural nets that it was possible to train on computers that
能够在当时的计算机硬件条件下训练
existed then, and that performed really well.
并且表现很好的深度神经网络应用之一
Convolutional neural networks are based on the idea of replicated features.
卷积神经网络起源于重复特征的思想
So, because objects move around and show up on different pixels, if we have a
由于物体会到处移动 在不同的像素点上出现 如果我们有
feature detector that's useful in one place in the image, it's likely that the
一个特征检测器在图像的某个位置起作用 有很大可能
same feature detector will be useful somewhere else.
这个特征检测器能够在其他位置派上用场
So, the idea is to build many different copies of the same feature detector in all
所以这里的思路是在所有不同的位置
the different positions. If you look on the right I've shown you
采用相同的特征检测器 右边的这个图展示了
three feature detectors, which are replicas of each other.
三个特征检测器 它们分别是各自的复制品
Each of them has weights to nine pixels. And those weights are identical between
每个包含对应于9个像素点的权重 这些权重对于
the three different feature detectors. So the red arrow has the same weight on it
这三个特征检测器来说是完全相等的 也就是说三根红色的箭头有着一样的权重
for all three feature detectors. And when we learn we keep those red arrows
在学习的时候 我们保持这些红色的箭头
all having the same weight as each other and we keep the green arrows having all
拥有一样的权重 绿色的箭头
the same weight as each other. Even though the red and green arrows will
拥有一样的权重 而红色跟绿色箭头会有
have different weights. We could also try replicating across scale
不同的权重 我们也可以尝试在不同的比例
and orientation but that's much more difficult and expensive and probably not a
和方位上复制特征 但这样会更困难复杂并且
good idea. Replication across position greatly
不一定是个好主意 在不同的位置复制特征大大
reduces the number of free parameters that you have to learn.
减少了需要学习的自由参数的数量
So those 27 pixels that you see in those three replicated detectors only have nine
这3个检测器中的27个像素只有9个
different weights. Now we don't just want to use one feature
不同的权重值 我们需要的不止一种特征
type. So we're going to have many maps.
所以我们会有很多的特征图 (feature maps)
Each map will have replicas of the same feature, features that are constrained to
每一个特征图提取图像不同位置的
be identical in different places. And then different maps will learn to
相同特征 不同的特征图
detect different features. This allows each patch of the image to be
会学习提取不同的特征 这就让图像的每一个区块
represented by features of many different types.
能够表示为很多不同的特征的集合
Replicated features fit in nicely with back propagation that is it's easy to
重复特征的思想与反向传播并不冲突
learn using back propagation. In fact its easy to modify the back
很容易用反向传播来训练模型 实际上我们可以对反向传播做一些简单的
propagation algorithm incorporate any linear constraint between the weights.
改动来考虑权重之间的任意线性约束
So what we do is we compute the gradients as usual.
具体的做法是我们先照常计算梯度
But then we modify the gradients, so that if the weight satisfied the linear
然后在参数更新前对梯度进行修改 来使它们满足
constraint before the weight update, they'll also satisfy the linear constraint
这些线性约束 这样参数在更新之后也会满足
after the weight update. So, the simplest example is we want two
相同的约束 举个最简单的例子 我们想让两个
weights to be equal. We want w1 to equal w2.
权重保持相等 比如 w1 = w2
That would be true if we start off with W1 equal to W2.
要满足这个约束 我们可以初始化 w1 等于 w2
And then we make sure that the change in W1 is always equal to the change in W2.
然后我们只要保证 w1 的更新总是 与 w2 的更新值相等
The way we do that is we compute the gradient of the arrow with respect to W1.
方法是分别计算 w1 的梯度
And the gradient with respect to W2. And then we use the sum or average of
和 w2 的梯度 然后用两个梯度的和或者平均
those two gradients for both W1 and W2. By using weight constraints like that, we
来更新 w1 以及 w2 通过使用这样的权重约束
can force back propagation to learn replicated feature detectors.
我们能够促使反向传播学习 重复的特征检测器
There's quite a lot of confusion in the literature about what replicated feature
很多文献对重复特征检测器所起的作用
detectors are actually achieving. Many people claim they're achieving
有误解 很多人认为它们的作用是
translation invariance. And that's not true.
平移不变性 这是不正确的
Well at least it's not true in the activities of the neurons.
至少从神经元的活动来说是不准确的
So if you look at the activities, what replication features achieve is
如果你观察神经元的活动 重复特征达到的效果是
equivariance not invariance. An example should make that clear.
同变性而不是不变性 举个例子应该更好理解
Here's an image, and the black dots are the activated neurons.
这里是一幅图片 黑点表示 被激活的神经元
Here's a translated image. And notice the black dots have also
这是一幅平移后的图片 我们可以观察到这些黑点也
translated. So the image changed and the
跟着平移了 也就是说图片发生了变化
representation also changed by just as much as the image.
而从这幅图片中提取的特征也发生了 相同的变化
That's equivariance not invariance. There is somethings invariant, and that's
这是同变性而不是不变性 不过确实有不变的地方
the knowledge. So if you learn replicative feature
那就是学到的知识 如果你学到了重复的特征
detectors, if you know how to detect a feature in one place, you'll know how to
检测器 你知道如何在某个位置检测 一种特征 那么你同样可以
detect that same feature in another place. And it's important to note that we're
在另一个位置检测同样的特征 很重要的一点是我们
achieving equivariance in the activities and invariance in the weights.
在神经元激活层面达到的是同变性 在权重方面达到的是不变性
If you want to achieve some invariance in the activities, what you need to do is
如果你想在神经元活动层面达到一定的 不变性 你需要做的是
pool the acts replicative feature detectors.
对重复特征做池化 (pooling) 的操作
So you can get a small amount of translation in variance at each level of a
你能够在深度神经网络的每一层 达到少部分的平移不变性
deep net, by averaging full neighboring replicated detectors.
通过将所有邻接的特征检测器的输出做平均
One advantage of this is that it reduces the number of inputs for the next layer.
这么做的优势之一是减少了 下一层网络的输入数量
So that we can have more different maps, allowing us to learn more different kinds
这样我们就可以有更多的特征图 能够在下一层中学到更多的不同种类的
of features in the next layer. It actually works slightly better to take
特征 实际上更好的一种做法是
the maximum of four neighboring feature detectors, rather than an average, but
取四个邻接特征检测器输出的最大值 而不是平均值
there is a problem. And the problem is that after several
但是这么做有一个问题 那就是在做了几层这样的
levels of doing this kind of pooling, we've lost precise information about where
池化操作之后 我们丢失了图片中物体的精确位置信息
things are. That's okay if we just want to recognize
如果我们只是想识别图片是不是一张人脸 的话这个问题不大
that it's a face. The fact that we've got a few eyes, and a
几个眼睛、一个鼻子和
nose, and a mouth floating about in vaguely the same position is very good
一张嘴在大致相近的位置出现已经
evidence that it's a face. But if you want to recognize whose face it
是人脸的很好证据 但是如果你想要识别出这张脸是谁
is, you need to use the precise spatial relationships between the eyes and between
你需要利用五官之间精确的相对空间关系
the nose and the mouth. And that's been lost by these
而那些信息已经在这些
convolutional neural nets. I'll come back to that issue later on.
卷积神经网络中丢失了 我们之后还会讨论到这个问题
So the first impressive example of a convolution on your own end was done by
卷积神经网络的第一个非常成功的应用
Yann Lecun and his collaborators who developed a really good recognizer for a
是 Yann LeCun 和他的合作者们开发的一个 用于手写数字的识别器
hundred digits. In it had many hidden layers.
这个模型有很多个隐层
In each layer, it had many maps of replicated units.
每一层都会有很多个特征图
And it had pooling between layers. So you pool adjacent replicated units
隐层之间有池化相邻单元的操作
before you send them to the next layer. But I also used a wide net that could cope
然后再将池化的结果传到下一层 另外我们还用到了一个宽的网络
with several characters at once. And that would work even if the characters
能够识别多个字符 而且就算数字有重叠也能识别
overlapped. So you didn't have to segment out
这样你就不需要将单个字符分割出来
individual characters before you fed them to their net.
再输入到神经网络中
And something which, people often forget, is that they used a clever way of training
人们经常遗忘的一点是他们使用了 一种精巧的方法来训练
a complete system. They weren't just training a recognizer of
一个完整的系统 他们并不只是训练针对单个字符的
individual characters. They were training a complete system, so
识别器 他们训练了一个完整的系统
that you put in pixels at one end and you get out whole zip codes at the other end.
输入图片的像素点 你就能得到对应的邮政编码
And in training that system they used a method that would now be called maximum
在训练的时候这个系统使用了现在被称为 最大间距的方法
margin. But when they did it, it was way before
不过那个时候这个概念还没有被提出
maximum margin had been invented. The net they used was at one point
他们提出的这个神经网络模型曾经
responsible reading about for ten percent of the checks in North America.
负责北美百分之十的支票的识别任务
So it was of great practical value. There were some very nice demos on that,
这有着很大的实用性价值 关于这个模型有一些非常好的演示
on Yann's workpaget. You should really go look at them.
在 Yann 的网站上 大家应该去看一下
Look at all of them. Because they show you just how.
都看一遍 这些演示展示了
Well it copes with variations in size, orientation, position, overlap of digits,
这个模型应对不同大小、方向、位置 的数字 相互重叠的数字以及
and all sorts of background noise that would, would kill most methods.
不同的背景噪点的能力 大部分方法不具备这种能力
The architecture of LeNet-5 looks like this.
LeNet5 模型的结构是这样的
There's an input, which is pixels. And then there's a whole sequence of
首先有一堆输入像素点 然后有一系列的
feature maps followed by sub sampling. So in the C1 feature map, the six
特征图和子采样层 (即池化层) 例如在 C1 这一层中有6个
different maps, each which is 28 by 28. Of those maps contain small features that
不同的特征图 每一个的大小是28x28 这些特征图包含着
just look at I think three by three pixels.
3x3的特征检测器提取的特征
And their weights are constrained together.
这些检测器的权重都是共享的
So per map there's only about nine parameters.
所以每个特征图只有9个参数
That makes learning much more efficient. It means you need much less data.
使得训练过程更加高效 需要的数据量大大减少
Then after the feature map, there's what they call sub-sampling which is now called
在特征图之后是他们称为子采样的操作 现在被称为池化操作
pooling. And so, you pool together the outputs of a
你把 C1 中一堆相邻的重复特征
bunch of neighboring replicated features in C1.
合并到一起
And that gives you a smaller map, which will then provide the input to the next
这样得到一个较小的特征图 作为下一层的输入
layer, which is discovering more complicated replicated features.
从而提取更为复杂的特征
As you go up this hierarchy, you get features that are much more complicated,
随着层数的提升 你会得到越来越复杂的特征
but are more invariant to position. Here's the errors that LeNet5 made.
它们对位置也越来越不敏感 这张图列出了 LeNet5 识别错的数字
And this shows you the data that it's dealing with is quite tricky.
从这可以看出它处理的数据是很复杂的
There's 10,000 test cases, and these are the 82 errors that it makes.
一共有10,000个测试样本 这是它识别错误的所有82个样本
So it's doing better than 99% correct. Nevertheless, most of the errors it makes
识别成功率在99%以上 但是大部分的错误都是
are the things that people find quite easy to recognize.
人们觉得很容易就能识别的数字
So there's some way to go still. Nobody knows the human error rate on this
所以这里还有一些提升的空间 没有人知道人类在这个数据集上的错误率
data. But it's probably twenty to 30 errors.
据估计在20到30个错误之间
Of course the might-be digits that LeNet5 got right and you would get wrong.
当然有可能 LeNet5 识别正确的数字 而人会识别错
So you have to be careful in estimating the error rate.
所以在估计错误率的时候要小心
You can't just look at these 82 and ask which ones you'll get right and which ones
你不能只看这82个样本然后 统计哪些你能识别出来哪些不能
you'll get wrong. You have to worry about all those other
你还得去看所有其他 LeNet5 识别
ones that Lynette Five might've got right and you might've got wrong.
正确的样本 而你有可能识别不出
I'm now want to go to a very general point, about how to inject prior knowledge
我们现在要讨论一个很宽泛的概念 如何在机器学习问题中加入先验知识
in machine learning, and it applies particularly to neural networks.
这个对神经网络也非常适用
We can put in prior knowledge as it is done in the net five, by the design of the
就像 LeNet5 一样 我们可以通过 设计网络结构来加入先验知识
network. We can have local connectivity.
我们可以有局部连接性
We can have weight constraints. Or we can choose neuro-activites that are
可以对权重进行约束 也可以根据需要解决的任务来
particularly appropriate for the task we're doing.
选择合适的神经元激活函数
This is much less intrusive than trying to hand-engineer the futures.
这比直接手动加工特征要系统化得多
But it still prejudices the network towards a particular way of solving the
但是这样还是会让网络模型偏向 我们脑中的某种解决问题的特定方式
problem that we had in mind. We have an idea about how to do object
我们对如何做物体识别有一个思路
recognition by gradually making bigger and bigger features.
那就是逐部提取越来越高层次的特征
And by replicating these features across space.
并在空间的不同位置对相同特征进行提取
And we force the network to do it that way.
我们就促使网络模型按照这样的方式工作
There is an alternative way to put in prior knowledge that gives the network a
有另一种整合先验知识的方式 能够赋予网络模型更大的自由度
much freer hand. What we can do is use our prior knowledge
我们可以利用先验知识来
to get a whole lot more training data. One of the first examples of this was work
获得更多的训练数据 这方面最早的例子之一是
by Hofmann and Tresp on trying to model what happens in a steel mill.
Hofmann 和 Tresp 的炼钢炉模型
They wanted to know the relationship between what comes out of the steel mill
他们想知道炼钢炉的产物和
and various input variables, and they actually had an, big old Fortran simulator
不同的输入变量之间的关系 他们实际上使用的是一个 Fortran 模拟器
that would allow them to simulate the steel mill.
用于模拟炼钢炉的环境
Of course, the simulator wasn't reality. It was making all sorts of approximations.
当然模拟器跟真实的环境是有差别的 模拟器采取了各种的近似方法
So they had real data, and also a simulator.
他们有真实的数据和一个模拟器
And what they did was run the simulator in order to create some synthetic data.
他们利用模拟器生成了一些合成数据
We then added that to the real data, and showed that they could do better than just
再把这些合成数据跟真实数据合并起来 他们发现这样做比仅仅使用
using the real data alone. If I remember right, their great, big
真实数据要更为有效 如果我没记错 他们的那个巨型
Fortran simulator was only worth a few dozen extra real examples, but
Fortran 模拟器仅仅贡献了几十个样本
nevertheless, they made the point. Of course, if you generate a lot of
就算这样它们还是起到了作用 当然 如果使用了大量的
synthetic data, it may make learning take much longer.
合成数据会使训练时间大大增长
So in terms of the speed of learning, it's much more efficient to put in knowledge by
所以就训练时间而言 像 LeNet5 那样以限制连接和约束权重
using things like connectivity and weight constraints, as was done in Lynette five.
的方式来整合知识是效率更高的方式
But as computers get faster, this other way of putting in knowledge, by generating
但随着计算速度的加快 这种生成合成数据的方式
synthetic examples, begins to look better and better.
表现得越来越好
In particular, it allows optimization to discover clever ways of using the
特别是它使得优化方法能够找到更精巧的
multilayer network that we didn't think of.
利用多层网络的方法 而这些方法我们可能都没有考虑过
If fact, we might never fully understand how it does it.
实际上我们可能永远不能完全理解它的原理
If we just want good solutions to a problem, that might be fine.
如果我们只是想要获得一个问题的较优解 这可能问题不大
So using the idea of synthetic data, there's a brute force approach to
利用合成数据的思想 有一种暴力途径来解决
handwritten digit recognition. Lenet5 uses knowledge about invariances to
手写数字识别 LeNet5 从不变性的知识出发
design the connectivity and the weight sharing and the pooling.
设计了模型中的局部连接性、权重共享 以及池化操作
And that achieves about 80 errors. Adding a lot more tricks, including
他们达到了80个错误 通过加入包括合成数据在内的更多技巧
synthetic data, [UNKNOWN] was able to get that down to about 40 errors.
Marc'Aurelio Ranzato 把错误降到了40个
A group in Switzerland, led by [UNKNOWN] went to town with injecting knowledge by
由 Jürgen Schmidhuber 领导的瑞士的 一个研究小组以创造合成数据
putting in synthetic data. They put a lot of work into creating very
的方式来注入知识 他们在创造有指导性的合成数据
instructive synthetic data. So for every real training case, they
方面做了很多努力 对每一个真实的训练样本
transformed it to make many more training examples.
他们通过变换得到更多的训练样本
They then trained a large net with many units per layer, many layers on a graphic
之后他们在 GPU 上训练了一个很大的网络 网络模型有很多层 每一层有很多隐藏节点
processor unit. The graphics processor unit gave them a
GPU 让计算的速度加快了13倍
factor of thirteen computation. And because of all the synthetic data they
由于他们加入的各种合成数据
put in, it didn't overfit. If they just use a large net with a GPU.
模型没有过拟合 如果他们只是用 GPU 训练一个大型网络
It would have been a disaster that over fitted terribly that they would have done
那么会发生很严重的过拟合现象
on the training data but terribly on the test data.
在训练数据上表现完美但是 在测试数据上则很差
So they were really combining three tricks.
他们联合使用了这三种技巧
Put your effort in to generating lots of synthetic data then train a large net on a
生成了很多合成数据 然后在 GPU 上训练了一个大型网络
gpu. They managed to achieve 35 errors like
他们就这样成功地达到了35个错误
that. So here's the 35 errors that they got.
这里列出了那35个错误
The top printed digit is the right answer. And the bottom two digits are their top
顶部的数字代表了正确的答案 底部的两个数字则是模型预测的
two answers. What you'll notice is that they nearly
前两名 我们可以观察到正确答案几乎
always get the right answer in their top two.
总在前两名中
There's only five cases where they don't. With some more work by building several
只有5个样本的正确答案没有在前两名 的预测中 通过搭建几个
different models like this and then using a consensus to decide what the digit was,
类似这个的不同模型并使用 投票的方式来决定预测的数据
they managed to get down to about 25 errors.
他们成功地将错误数降到25个
And that must be around about the human error rate.
而这正好接近人类的错误率
One question this work raises is how do you tell if a model makes 30 errors is
这个研究提出的一个问题是 人们怎么判断错30个的模型
really better than a model that makes 40 errors.
是不是真的比40个错误的模型要优越
Is that significantly different? Rather surprisingly, it turns out it
这个差别真的显著吗? 令人没想到的是这个要
depends on which errors they make. The numbers then provide you enough
依具体识别的错误而定 错误数量并不能提供足够的
information. You have to know which ones they get wrong
信息 你需要知道哪些样本模型识别错了
and which ones they get right. So this statistical test called the
哪些样本模型识别对了 这个统计检验叫做
McNemar test that uses the particular errors and is far more sensitive than just
McNemar 检验 由于用到了特定的错误信息 它比只利用错误数量的检验方法要更为
using the numbers. Let me give you an example.
敏感 举个例子
If you look at this two by two tape. It shows you, in the top left hand corner,
我们来看这个2x2的表 在左上角显示的是
how many examples Model one got wrong and Model two also got wrong.
模型1和模型2都预测错误的样本数
That's 29. And in the bottom right, it shows you how
29个 在右下角显示的是
many examples Model one got right and Model two also got right.
两个模型同时预测正确的样本数
And in the Magnema Test, you can just ignore those numbers in black.
在 McNemar 检验中 你可以直接忽略这些黑色的数字
All you're interested in is ones where Model one got it right and Model two get
你感兴趣的是那些 模型1预测正确但模型2
it wrong, or Model two got it right and Model one get it wrong.
预测错误的样本 或者反过来模型2 预测正确而模型1预测错误的样本
And if you look at that, there's an eleven to one ratio, and it turns out that's
从表中可以看出这两个数值的比值 是1比11 而这个比值其实是
pretty significant. Model two is definitely better than model
很显著的 模型2肯定比模型1更好
one. That didn't happen by accident, almost
而这几乎不可能是偶然的结果
certainly. By contrast if you look at this table,
相比之下我们来看这张表
again. Model one is making 40 hours, model two is
模型1预测错误为40个 模型2
making 30 hours, but now model one is winning fifteen times when model two loses
则为30个 但现在的情况是模型1 在15个样本上表现比模型2要好
and model 2's winning 25 times when model one loses.
而模型2则在25个样本上表现更为出色
That difference is not very significant so we wouldn't be confident that model two is
这个差别并不显著 所以模型2要优于模型1的结论
better than model one.
置信度不高 翻译 Yijun Xiao